hi everyone welcome to another awaking
from the meaning crisis discord QA
we have a return guest tonight layman
Pascal thank you so much for being here
layman you can hear me right layman here
yep okay great so so last time we we
talked about yeah well a lot about
shamanism in a in a sort of broad
perspective but I but I'd like to bring
it down to start off tonight bring it
down to the more practical what you know
you know here on this discord and in
this awakening from the meeting crisis
community we we've been trying to
implement Ecology's of practices we've
been really trying to come up with you
know take take from established rituals
and borrow from them but also think
about what are new rituals that we could
we could enact in terms of serious play
to help to help foster our perspectival
and participatory ways of knowing and I
suspect that there there's a lot that we
can borrow from from shamanistic
practices you know to sort of you know
to apply to to us today you know for
example I understand you know the you
know the ancient shamans would for
example have rituals where they would
embody a bird and that would help them
with hunting as they got a better sense
of how how how the birds fly and how
they act and you know we we were we were
doing some ecstatic we have this
practice we've started doing ecstatic
dance nights here and during one of the
songs suddenly occurred to me to try to
embody a zombie you know John John uses
the symbol of the zombie so for that one
song I just sort of tried to act like a
zombie and I and I thought you know
there's probably something shamanistic
about about this and and maybe there are
are things that we can borrow from
shamanism in our rituals today so I like
to hear your thoughts on that I think
one particular aspect of shamanism is
what I might call proprioceptive
imagination where you try to in a way
like harness your mirror neurons to
duplicate the performative structure of
some other part of the universe with the
idea that you could get a more than
conscious understanding of how its
operating you increase the degree to
which your nervous system is duplicating
it trying to understand truly physically
posture early asana so to speak going on
with that structure so I think one of
the things the ancient shamans tended to
do was to enact this receptive
imagination with various creatures that
impressed them I think it's a very
general skill I know that John is
interested in the way that some
scientists have entered into a similar
kind of relationship with Mars rovers
you could do it with fundamentally any
structure or any pattern of information
that we're working with in the universe
one of the interesting things that
Einstein said was that he tried to think
with his muscles
I think that's overlooked by a lot of
people who are doing intellectual work
or trying to understand the universe
whether that means the cosmos or their
own moment in history and what gets
overlooked is the the need to have a
physiological somatic flowing engagement
with the pattern that you're trying to
think of the proud minute you're trying
to understand so what would that look
like for us today if you could bring it
down just do very practical I don't know
you can bring it out to step by step but
if we're trying to come up trying to
identify such a pattern that we should
embody how how should we go about trying
to come up with how to do this well I
would probably start small you know
start like the ancient shamans would
have star to start with a tree or a rock
or a bird or something that you see in a
very simple way every day
a number of different things try to
build up the skill and capacity or you
try to transpose that on to example
Derna t might be a system you think wow
how could I get in touch with the mo
spirit of modernity so to speak so that
I could understand and critique it at a
more than intellectual level and have to
embody its patterns but I can only do
that if I've had some practice trying to
embody patterns that are more viscerally
available to me but I would start like
the ancient shamans did is just try to
pick something in nature
try to imagine feeling and imagine doing
its structure so to speak there's a very
interesting interplay between shape and
activity the interesting things in terms
of human sexuality is that we let Mol's
tried to foreground features that are
gender polarized in order to initiate
mating practices so someone might put
their chest forward because that's a
gender indicator in the species but then
you see somebody who simply structurally
built as if their chest is always coming
forward and a lot of people have a
response to that but what I mean to
indicate by that is there's a very fuzzy
line between structure and gesture and
behavior there's a thing in terms of
thinking about a structure as if it was
a behavior and trying to embody that
behavior and have a system right we have
a system of instantly duplicating the
behaviors that we see is it all the time
we get stressed when we hear someone
expressing stress and we can tap into
that system try to treat structures that
we see in the world as if they are
behaviors I know that sounds really
abstract but like I was saying start
with really simple things but if you see
a tree try to you know imagine what it
would be like inside your own body and
nervous system to do that trying to
speak what would the gesture be what
activity is it up to that you could
duplicate and if you get a little bit
better at that skill then you could
transpose that into more abstract and
sociological and technological domains
and I guess there would be a fair amount
of observation a very careful officer
first what would the shamans do before
attempting to say embody a bird would
they spend a great deal of time
observing just everything they could
about about the bird or do you just sort
of jump into it and that's extremely
variable because everybody can do
everybody can milk perception in a
different kind of way right a lot of
much as you might gain new information
by watching something over a while they
never gain as much increase in
information as you gain in the first
split second right in the first
split-second of observation you go from
zero to a whole bunch of data you might
want to Adam break that data and flesh
it out and enrich it with further
observations especially you might want
to connect with different parts of
yourself with your in Sri and emotional
and intellectual and subconscious
responses to the perception of that
phenomenon at the same time a lot of
people might get almost everything they
need or almost everything that they can
get in that first split second before
they even do a socialized identification
process the interesting things to me
about Richard Fineman in his
autobiography he talks about the way his
father trained him to think about things
and his father would I did get him to
understand objects and patterns in
nature but he refused to tell him the
English word areas birds for various
trees for things like that he thought
that knowing the name sabotage the
learning process building fineman's case
this educational approach worked out
really well but it meant was had a lot
more time before he identified the
object motive to his cultural
information about that object
I'd say learn a lot more get a lot more
detail and that's very helpful
I'd say access multiple systems of your
own knowledge like sensing feeling and
thinking in order to get a very
comprehensive knowledge might also say
special attention to that split second
before you identify it before you label
it before you name it
the moment where you're getting the
maximum acceleration of information
where you go from not seeing it to
seeing it that's a huge jump most all of
its stylistic and effect is available to
you in that first moment we have a
particular challenge here where we're
trying to develop new rituals but we're
also doing it largely online you know
eventually you know with when COBIT
leaks surco bit sort of trails off we
might be able to start having in-person
meetings in various parts of the world
but but but for now we're stuck we're
stuck online how would a group embodying
ritual I don't know if you could almost
design one on the spot but what what
might we do together through a discord
call like this now although with the
video to to do do this practice so like
you said with the tree but do it with
each other a couple of things come to
mind immediately the first is that
everybody would need to pay attention to
their own current state of embodiment to
their neuro somatic feedback circuit
right what's going on in your physiology
what's going on in the space that you
imagine inside your body where is the
experience of your body feeding back
into itself in a kind of energetic
tingle sense how is that then responding
to the individuals who are speaking into
the rest of the group because I think
tending to that live information is very
important to this process and you do a
lot of information about how to talk
what you're doing in order to tune in at
the same time you've got a circle
through everybody right interesting when
you have one person be the center of the
speech but if want to do it like an
ancient get-together then everybody has
to cycle through enough times for
everybody to sort of feel each of the
participants and the other thing I would
say is it's it's dangerous to
overemphasize the rationale I've been in
a lot of groups where people have wanted
- I'm cycle through everyone and
everybody speak about you know why
they're here or what they're concerned
about and that's very useful they don't
also often cycle through irrational
elements right if we say everybody say a
completely meaningless thing would come
from a different part of them
it's cycled through and you had
everybody make a random noise or you had
everybody try to make a surrealistic
utterance of some kind that could be
involving the subconscious mind of the
group you'd be telling the subconscious
that it can play a role and in terms of
shamanism you pretty much want
subconscious intelligent so so would
that be sort of an exercise just to
start off a session you know everyone
make make a sound just any sound that
comes to mind absolutely you could do it
that way I mean I would spend to have a
couple of minutes where everybody spent
time feeling into their body I would
have everybody try to feel into their
body as everyone else spoke but then I
would cycle through and you could make a
noise you could say a random thing try
to say something that doesn't make sense
to you that speaks to your feeling of
the effect of the group that maybe and
and then if we wanted to have an
embodiment exercise you know like like
the tree or an ant or or the or the
Internet can you describe how you would
envision something like that in a group
setting like this you could just pick
something that probably everybody has a
good mental image of way the ancient
shamans left their marks on rock walls
probably speaks to things that they
found simple enough to communicate about
which is the deer or here's a guy with a
wolf's head or something like that
here's an arrow we all kind of have
instantaneous reactions to a lot of
basic animals and a lot of basic
scenarios that our ancestors went
through for thousands or millions of
years if you were to take something like
that right like everybody think of
Jaguar everybody think of a snake what
does a snake feel like how do you
feel when you see the snake a snake rive
inside your body so to speak
let your mirror neurons activate
response to the snake good cycle through
everybody doing that I think if you took
a very simple you know way mythically
charged unconsciously active pattern
that everybody could get in on might be
a way to move one step forward in a
group ritual and what do you have people
just act it out or where they verbalize
what's going through their mind at the
time you could do either I mean if
you're doing it in an audio format then
their individual acting out isn't going
to be available to the other members so
it would be useful for them individually
but there's this extra effect it
compounds when the other people have
access to the way that you're responding
to bring the group intelligence to speed
if you were just doing audio then you
would definitely want everybody to
articulate something response to that
phenomenon so they get well if you were
doing video then people could act it out
it may be easier for a lot of people to
think of something and say it than it is
for them to figure out how to move that
way but I would say that moving is
superior to speech in a lot of ways in
terms of the levels of the brain and
psyche that a taps into which is where
the shamans were primarily active right
in very deep primordial areas of the
brain rather than socialize front
regions of the brain coming up with our
own rituals like this well you can't be
chanting it's fantastic if you want a
lesson on chanting just to make noise to
make rhythmic intonation sounds and see
how you are reverberating relative to
others allows you to coordinate with
them but it also is a very fundamental
form
self-expression and passes a lot of the
social limitations of the intellect and
what what so what what do these if we do
these practices I mean what should we
expect a second-order effects what do
these practices afford us all
immediately I would say there's two
kinds of things just is insight into
whatever aspect of reality that you're
focusing on life your look snakes or
you're looking at the internet looking
like Einstein did at Lightspeed you're
likely to get is some insights into that
area of the universe the other hand like
I was saying when I was on here last
time my sense of what spiritual practice
means is the coordination of the
subsystems within the individual to
produce a Gestalt excess that can then
feed back onto the individual a second
thing that you would get out of these
kinds of practices is a new kind of
balance between the parts of yourself be
folding in different areas of your own
psyche different psychological and
neurological subsystems would come
online at the same time be forced to
interact and therefore achieve a new
kind of balance and be Nevil n't side
effect of effectively achieving balance
of that kind is that you get a little a
little extra you get a bonus you get the
gestalt resonance effect
there's intrinsically satisfying and I
think it's what provides us with the
energy for growth members what ecology
of practices do you follow he wants to
say it's eclectic that just is a way of
circuiting the attempt to do an
elaborate description of all the
different things I do I try to make my
life out of practice so it would be a
very involved topic to go through of my
meditation I have my afternoon
meditation they're quite different I
have
my sexual practice I have my breathing
practice I have my food practice I have
my physical exercise practice I have my
working with nature practice the degree
to which you can intentional eyes your
activities use them as opportunities to
provide you with the convergence of
multiple internal and interpersonal
factors becomes addictive and highly
useful as a life of that answers your
question but I don't follow a specific
set what I've done is experiment broadly
with many for the patterns of
commonality between them take my
favorites and make them compete against
each other then ultimately find ones
that are largely urgent out of my own
intelligence and which apply very nicely
to my life very helpful Manuel you have
a question yeah so we have this running
theory on the server that a lot of
people in the modern world are stuck
prospectively we're having this idea
about getting them unstuck when drowning
them back some flexibility and I was
hoping to get your insight in how some
kind of shamanic practice might leave
like profound lasting impact with the
emphasis on the lasting and then how we
might use symbols in connection to this
to afford these ideas
the symbol part is settle and more
involved the issue of missing taking
perspectives
it is really well studied as a method of
enhancing human in consent flexibility
getting us past the perspectives in
which our culture currently finds itself
but that can be I don't know if you know
again Perot she's big mind practice are
the kinds of Gestalt and internal Family
Therapy where you take different
perspectives in yourself they're all
very similar to what the shamans did
which was try to get into the
perspective of different aspects of the
system spirit Kennedy we consider
getting into the perspective of
ecological entities to be a subset of
the general pattern of and to take a lot
of different ways to do that it's
extremely useful think it's a skill set
that enables people to move past the
current civilization stuckness even if
we were to change our socio-economic and
drill biases would still remain stuck
unless we had a very generalized
capacity and interest taking new
perspectives and it big to them of that
answers your question you have to follow
up on that well so the idea would be to
shock people right out of their current
perspective but they also needed to be
like like it lure right like some some
intrinsically motivating elements to
keep them hooked on the new mode of
being so so that's where I was trying to
go with the question and then the
symbols was also something I liked you
to expend them I think
if you can get people to the place where
they think their own development is the
key to their feeling of power you can
convince them that taking different
perspectives is going to make them
stronger make them deeper give them more
being so to speak I don't know that you
have to trick or shock them you just
have to sell them on the idea that they
are going to feel themselves more
intensely they're able to absorb these
other perspectives and in order to do
that what they have to do is listen to
perspectives they don't like or that
seem foreign or alien to them in a very
simple way it could be just listening to
somebody who's politically opposite from
you and trying to figure out how you
would justify their own values their
arguments more elaborate way it could be
try to see yourself through the eyes of
a raven I'm still not entirely sure what
you mean by symbols because symbols is a
term that could mean a lot of different
things so the idea would be that we
wouldn't personally do it right like so
we designed like a game which gave
affordances right like would place
people in a certain relationship and
then they'd explore it so it'd be I have
to be engaging in some way and it'd have
has to grab the attention of the person
themselves right it has to be
Mima fireable and and the symbols would
be a way of having different layers of
meaning being connected to similar
things right so so that idea you could
integrate in the game and you could have
like a path that's around a symbol or
something where you get there
circumambulated that makes more sense
that's a very interesting idea think if
you can get people to try to speak from
a perspective not their own especially
if the perspective they're trying to
speak from is one that bothers them
you're in a very good
to teach their brain to know the other
perspective and they do that almost
immediate consequence is a sense of
freedom and empowerment for the
individual because brain has now
colonized a territory that they
previously excluded now own the energy
that they had projected onto the other
any any system in which you could get
people to try to talk from perspective
that seems foreign to them especially if
it's perspective that upsets them and
they're they're likely to be able to
access an energy that will become
progressively addictive to them because
that energy does increase the complexity
of their being increases the
sophistication of their nervous system
it will like it if they keep doing it
for a while okay thanks thank you Lord
dr. doom just wants to know what does
shamanism mean to you a good question
Lord dr. doom
omen ism it's a tricky term because for
me personally am I not that interested
in people who self-identify as shamans
and I'm not that interested in people
who are officially designated as shamans
by their indigenous group much more
interested in shamanism as a general
human phenomenon has existed throughout
history but which in a which sense
stands at the beginning of all human
yogic and spiritual traditions I think
of shamanism as a fundamentally embodied
illogically oriented City adaptive
arm of proto spirituality in which the
basic skills that lead to religion and
spirituality and human development and
wisdom practices all emergent out of
human instincts within natural contexts
reason I like that so much is that we're
in a situation
now that is kind of parallel or a
harmonic overtone to the archaic
situation situation as a civilization
where we need to pattern ourselves
relationship to ecology we need to be
much more embodied in terms of our
thinking will be more psychedelic in
terms of our thinking and to be able to
generate as of ritual and consecration
rather than rely on the forms that we've
inherited we need to be able to form
individual search into weirdness and try
to help the tribe with the results of
our individual inquiry into unusual
domains I think that's a huge current it
echoes very strongly the types of
practices we can imagine were present
prior to the recorded history human
spirituality and religion and metal
practice and so for me shamanism means
that original state also the way in
which the capacities of that original
state apply to our currents that is
fascinating thank you can I ask a
follow-up just please okay so I've been
into philosophy for for multitude
reasons I want to understand the
universe first of all but then at once I
started learning from people like Jordan
Peterson John vaycay became very
interested in existential philosophy and
I think that that touches exactly on
what shamanism is that that embodied
experience so which you have any
philosophical existential elements to
that like in the form of practice like
what would what would that look like in
a form of practice to you and say maybe
your favorite your favorite sense of
practice in an existential sense
not sure entirely because my my
favorites shift instantly breeding that
flow the way a surfer operates with the
water is very important to me I want to
necessarily privilege any one thing as
my favorite type of practice but I would
say that if you take your internal work
to nature as much as you can you make
sure that the overall sensation of the
inside of your body is a factor in any
of your practices you were doing any
kind of meditation the total interior
simultaneity of sensation within the
body irrelevant to you your subconscious
information system be something that's
always on the tip of your tongue that
you should always be thinking that
there's a part of you that's there
smarter than you or can provide some
information that you don't currently
have and you are template of lis
available to that information and
looking for information whether it makes
immediate rational sense to you or not I
think those two things are peers that I
work into a lot of my practices Bell is
trying to do as much as I can with
nature with the biosphere in the forest
in the water obviously one of the things
that annek traditions around the world
have focused on is psychological effect
of elemental powers that means very
simplistic way earth air water and fire
you know the Asian system is a little
bit different but to make physical
contact and to immerse yourself in and
smoke and water and foam and wind and
forest ache and River all those kind of
things provided tremendous reset to the
human organism
and tremendous opportunity to apply our
other meditative and contemplative
exercises that makes any sense
yeah that's utterly fascinating I really
like it's completely enlightened to me
because you you didn't choose like the
having mode like you're you're in this
meta sense where you don't have just one
practice like the practice to you is the
fact that you're going in and out of
multiple practices and constantly
shifting and reintegrating so I really
like that thank you I just want to come
back to something you just said make see
if I'm reading something in or just to
make sure you said you weren't too
interested in the people today who call
themselves shamans and I didn't know if
there was some sort of negative tinge
there or some sort of implied
accusations of being charlatans or not
being real so to speak
so just that I don't know so in any
given circumstance I have no reason to
believe anyone who asserts themselves as
a shaman is more or less likely than
anyone else to be a shaman do I have any
reason to believe anyone who is asserted
by their tribe to be a shaman is more or
less likely than anyone else to be a
shaman they could be might not be I just
don't think that self assertion or
official ization like social sanction
whether it's a certificate you get after
your shamanism retreat weekend or
whether it say an endorsement you get
from your tribe in the Amazon don't
think social official ization a good
basis for determining who's actually
embodying shamanic intelligence is don't
know so I don't have a negative opinion
about it I have a negative opinion about
it as a validation approach may or may
not be what I mean so so what what do
you look for to figure out if somebody
is more authentic so to speak
I think it's a it's a very rich
phenomenon so you have to get to know
somebody right I'm looking for our
things like person who lives in a way
that passes through a lot of different
states of consciousness aim for someone
who is deeply involved with what we
might metaphorically refer to as natural
powers but who's always looking for
something deeper in phenomenon looking
for someone whose spirituality is
embodied and for someone who's
psychedelically intelligent to some
degree looking for someone who is trying
to bring their rational intellect
together with their subconscious prompts
looking for someone who is constantly
moved try to bring their successes in
terms of personal development and state
change into harmony with their personal
tribe their network of individuals they
think they can provide something to of
that our ways of looking at an organic
shop and so to speak rather than a
socially designated I think we were
having a conversation yesterday with
Alan and one of the things he mentioned
actually where shamans and the fact that
there are groups where even if they're
warring the shaman can in the middle of
the war go between the tribes without
falling prey to the tribal tendencies
for war for example and so I'm sort of
wondering at that point what the
connection is between shamanism and
sacred ism or the sacred and and what we
can sort of learn and you can integrate
you know in terms of shamanic practices
to a group and and and maybe you could
comment a little on how how the one
having one shaman can service a group of
people even in different tribes for it
what that relationship sort of looks
like to you that's a great question I
think it has a couple of different
components and one of them is the shaman
has a socially elevated position in the
Asian cultures right the same way that
Lamas had a socially elevated position
in the Himalayas for a thousand years
there are reforms of human society in
which the people that are involved in
these practices these wisdom cultivating
practices given a special protected and
elevated status and are involved in the
regular political and economic
activities of the society as special
observer commentators people say that
democracy goes back to a poet
philosopher Sol on in Athens so there's
this tremendous a tendency of societies
to Accord special status of insight to
these things Society tends to get off
track then try to involve these actors
fundamental participants in the
decisions that the society is making the
other side of it is bull who undergo
perspectival enrichment it's taking the
perspective of someone you hate or
taking the perspective of a nonhuman
animal the internet or the forest or the
world or the gods person tends after a
while evolve to a new level of richness
in terms of what their basic approach to
other human beings is person who stands
in a kind of transcendental perspective
position relative to their own tribe can
also stand in that position relative to
another tribe hey and we from ade we've
had to get an idea that maybe some of
the Mystics throughout history were
people who had particular neuro
pathologies
Mircea Eliade a some of the other early
scholars of shamanism found that the
shamans even in very indigenous
situations were typically the people in
the tribe had the most experiences the
greatest linguistic capacity and the
highest intelligence area often the
shaman in a given social context the one
who is capable of instinctively holding
higher perspectives that transcend that
context and included juxtaposition with
other content in sense that a person who
was world centric in their sensibility
come down on either side of an
ethnocentric nationalistic dispute
I think the shaman by virtue of
perspective taking practice come to
occupy a supra perspectival position
duplicable not just to their own tribe
but to multiple trucks and pathetically
is applicable to every side of every
dispute Wow one thing that sort of came
to mind there is that oh boy yeah I'm
gonna go here I think is that it sounds
like in some ways the more the idea of
IQ and intelligence in the Western world
has hijacked some of the features of
shamanism and so we're at some to some
degree holding the science class in in a
shamanic regard when it's not
appropriate because that's only one
dimension to the to the shamanic
experience and it's actually the other
dimension in some sense that's more
important the ability to do the
perspectival switch rather than the high
regard for the mental capacity we'll
call it in the in the propositional
space and it seems like we have some
confusion around that how does that make
you feel oh yeah I would agree with that
I would think that way we've done IQ for
the lab
little while for the modernity period so
to speak that we've hyper focused on
things that were adaptive intellectual
capacities in terms of the of
technological and market driven
circumstances in which we find ourselves
but I think that's a um derivation and a
specialization from the generalized
development of intelligence generalized
development of intelligence is Feldmann
of perspectives and the development of
intelligence on our multiple different
intelligence systems whether in the
Howard Gardner sense or the Ken Wilber
sense or just the heart mind and body
sense we have all these different
intelligence systems work on all of them
we can develop a generalized sense of
higher intelligence and AI that the
ancient shamans are the people in their
tribes with the greatest degree of
generalized intelligence so what we
currently think of as IQ is somewhat of
a specialized subset of generalized yeah
that's that excellent that gives me a
lot to chew on and it's interesting with
some of the current discussions we have
going on here so I appreciate that thank
you so we live in a skeptical age where
you know respect for some of the ancient
traditions have have elapsed let's say
what do you say to the modern skeptic
who sort of scoffs at these tiny types
of ancient practices and things you know
what do I have to learn from from these
from the Stone Age
these Stone Age practices I'll approach
it in a couple of ways first of all I
would say these people aren't skeptical
enough they're not uh yet skeptical of
their own metaphysical assumptions I
think he is generally post metaphysical
but that doesn't just mean on
traditional cosmological mythology it
also means beyond the sort of background
assumptions that characterize modernity
and mystic science as well that these a
lot of these things are still undecided
even the notion of fundamental
decidability is problematic so we have
to be very basically agnostic and
skeptical in a lot of ways and have a
good conscience about that so I would
say to the skeptic they should become
even more skeptical but also say that
human bio machinery is roughly constant
over the period of human history that we
we may be in different informational and
social circumstances now than our
archaic ancestors were but we have
fundamentally the same physiology and
the same neural physiology and therefore
the same basic needs and capacities that
they did might have been in uniquely
good circumstances to harness those
capacities from stances that we don't
necessarily have example if you wanted
to to grade all of the things you
understood to one whole who would have a
better chance of doing that if you only
knew a thousand things if you had knew a
million thing or ways in which more
primitive world spaces would provide
human beings who have the same bio
machinery as us a heightened opportunity
to bring themselves together to
coordinate themselves to access peak
experiences to rise to the heights of
what they're capable of a way that
people who have a much richer and more
complicated information and social
universe would have a much harder time
doing
do you see shamanistic practices like
cup coming back or do you do you see
alright are you optimistic about about
that possibility is see fragments of it
coming merging from all kinds directions
right the reason we're having this
discussion is it's coming up for me but
not just for me it's coming up for you
guys right the way John talks about
embodiment is a fundamental feature of
cognitive science the way all kinds of
different spiritual teachers are
focusing more on motion and embodiment
then maybe they did a hundred years ago
the way that we are all socially hyper
attuned to the fact that we are
coordinate with the patterns of organic
complexity that make the ecosystem run
way that psychedelics and altered states
of consciousness are becoming
decriminalized and renormalized in
therapy in art in sofia and spirituality
a lot of very optimistic signs that's
something that will eventually converge
on a new one ISM is bubbling up all over
the place
definitely I think John John's course is
what brought me back to having a respect
for these these ancient traditions so
hopefully we can play our part in that
at that as well
fact a lot of what are very simple ways
you know there was a study the details
escaped me in the mall but there was a
German town that was tested in the 1800s
for visual and auditory acuity and
students though a hundred years later
they thought it would be good to retest
them turned out that all of the students
at the same grade level had
significantly diminished in Victorian
visual acuity and when they tried to
theorize why that might be that guess
was that these kids were more exposed to
human technological environments
or stones and colors were very simple
and tailored to immediate up reception
by the human sense organs right we make
a red sign or we make a blue and yellow
sign we make things simple to see
because we want to communicate this
information hundred years ago people had
less of that kind of in signalling
system and more access to immersion in
natural circumstances which are highly
complex if you go into the woods and try
to follow a line vivoli you it ends up
skewing and splicing and branching end
up looking at a thousand different
shades of green you end up hearing
noises that are on the edge of your
ability to recognize it's the sense in
which a logically embedded organic
complexity fundamental driver of our
internal development and our
intelligence that if we fall too much
into simplified human social patterning
lose a huge range of richness in term
capacity and experience think a very
simple way of looking at what shamanic
experience has to bring back to us which
is the only the full richness of what
we're capable of the actual patterning
of the organic complexity of the
universe in which we are embedded and
from which we have sort of temporarily
insulated ourselves over the past few
hundred years and through a very
simplified human thought systems
actually thank you yeah I think I would
characterize myself as a skeptic
relative to II I suppose the spiritual
the spiritual claims of people I've met
who are shamans or purports to be
shamans or who make claims about
shamanism but I have a general respect
and value traditions which have
expressed many of the features that
you've talked about which
perhaps lapsed on contemporary human
cognition and so the question that I ask
although it may in some sense sound and
charitable is in the spirit of looking
to understand a way in which such
traditions can be preserved and was and
respected oh I just want to lay that as
the groundwork it seems to me that
shamanism
and wisdom traditions things like it
have been or as obliterated from
contemporary life and they've been out
competed by other sorts of ideas in
other ways of being perhaps lost a lot
has been lost there my concern remains
the same today that if in a world which
may become increasingly fractious and
there are Wars being fought over
particular belief systems they are
inculcated into their subscribers over
therefore so that they form efficient
combative groups often there are very
specific strategies about causing their
adherents not to think of other world
views not to consider other perspectives
and so those sorts of highly self
convinced world views it tend to be
extremely effective in Confederate in
people towards utopian ideals which
appear utopian only in so much as they
haven't considered or Brook their
possible downsides these sorts of views
have tended to out-compete others in
history and things like the facets of
shamanism that you mentioned
perspective-taking things which may be
enriching it tend to weaken groups when
it comes to all-out combat you know and
all against all war of ideas and and
perhaps even a war which becomes a
violent or military or even which just
becomes you know rhetorically
competitive and so my question is how as
a more rounded philosophy and a more
rounded enrichment of the self which is
is less likely to you know fight
to death in support of a simplistic
utopian notion how does it survive
against those ideas how do we ensure
that the arrow of history that doesn't
just reimagine eight as you said you
consider your hopeful science of a
weekend during but people are always
going to be tempted to kits and
solutions or its ideological or whether
it's say dietary right buddy with
children knows how easy it is for them
to converge on rapidly metabolizing
sugars that might not be good for them
there's always a maturational struggle
between it's good for us and the kinds
of skills and capacities we need to be
unfolding over time as a result of a
life of practice way we are immediately
tempted to converge on something that's
simplistic urging on something that's
simplistic in terms of ideas space
always going to be extremely tempting
when we are under stress and deprivation
conditions so that people falling back
on simplistic and totalitarian
winner-take-all mindsets it's a very
natural extension of the way that we've
set up our governmental and economic
systems around the world and as long as
you have those pressures on people we're
gonna tend to follow really dumb can its
contractive degenerative SIV versions of
these idea systems is in order for
people to take these practices as growth
practices for them to duplicate what
think went on with the archaic shaman in
order to become more perspectively rich
more complex deeper satisfied with your
beingness more capable of accessing the
variety of multi-dimensional capacities
that are within you capable of
contributing to a society that moves
forward qualitatively and the
anthropological and the ecological and a
more balanced in order to do that
you have to be depressurized enough to
do that if the pressure is on it right
if somebody comes into your house with a
gun when you're not that worried about
your somatic developmental practices
you've got to deal with the emergency
degree to which we've set up people to
feel like they're in an emergency and
they're gonna use the degenerative
version rather than the developmental
version of any idea system right yes III
do take that point but it does seem that
this emerged out of cultural coevolution
Oh
long before we'd set up modern societies
these ideas began to be extinguished oh
yeah I agree with everything you said
about you know that's the pathology how
do we do you think avoid it in a world
let's say where there are reawakening
Zoar let's say the harnessing of
religious idealism do shape groups into
conflict and your particular religious
idealisms which have a particular answer
a particular way to get to heaven and
which have you know obviously formed
great empires and there's kind of a a
revanche to reform these things and
governments around the world to the at
least we like that I can think of our
using them as way as ways to sort of
reform empires how in that world are
these ideas best defended I think agree
with the pathology you describe it well
how do we best defend what subtle and
precious and exploratory about these
things in the metaphorical world in
which yes
a stranger is in your house and they may
have a done a tend to think of religion
myself as the result of the Edible
integration of the different genres
operating in a society in a given epoch
for me the danger is not so much
religion religion that's adapted to
previous historical technological and
knowledge epochs I think one of the
problems we face today is that we are
sufficiently religion izing the current
knowledge universe so people feel the
tremendous lack of meaning and they tend
to regress back towards a previous
pledge universe that they felt was
massively integrated they're looking for
that Civ resonant intuition of all the
dimensions of life can't get it at the
current level of complexity very
naturally roll back to a simpler level
of complexity that is the general
supportive conditions are missing right
if they are in a better situation
physically better situation emotionally
and mentally helped wise biologically
culturally more information more
education fundamentally more experienced
from childhood onward up engaging in
growth practices and of understanding
themselves wanting to understanding
themselves you get organic self-esteem
trying to embrace things that are
different than themselves
so the whole lifestyle pattern that's
needed in order to support people in a
way that they could fundamentally make
that decision we're always going to be
at risk as we were at every period in
the past at risk of pathology and
degeneration after provide on the one
hand the support of conditions and the
other hand the kinds of internal
developmental practice that help people
grow beyond that and the people who have
done that can act as sort of anchors
which create a social space which
encourage other people to do that always
going to be a danger and it's not just
religion it's a set of ideas whatsoever
operate in this degenerative and
pathological and totalitarian fashion
what we need to do is set up the
liberabit life of practice but also the
range of support of sociological
physiological and political conditions
that enable people to deep to rise look
for the growth pathways rather than the
stress reaction path forms thanks very
much
manual you have a question we've been
trying to struggle with the idea of
charisma on the server and I think it's
related to being in contact with your
authentic self but I also think there's
a lack of at least healthy charismatic
people in modern society so do you see
any relationship to shamanism and do you
have any ideas about how to cultivate
charisma as a skill this was a complex
area obviously an aspect of it that is
simply performative anybody could adapt
themselves to a form of public acting
would come across as charismatic to
others often a lot of people we are
charismatic as celebrities are actually
very sad depressive looking characters
when you examine them closely I always
found Robin Williams very charismatic
but look at photos of him and you see
this big smile you have an immediate
response to his performative gesture of
smiling you look a little closer if you
look at his eyes and ignore your first
reaction and easily see the level of
depression there that led to his suicide
and some of his other behaviors part of
it is just performance it is physiology
people whose bodies are healthy in that
kind of a therapy sense and bodies that
allow stimulation patterns to move more
thoroughly through all their organs be
related to Kundalini practice in the
East bodies that allow more electricity
to move through them a certain
additional liveliness a certain capacity
to relate to their own electric fields
differ
sometimes charisma is performance
sometimes charisma is the projection of
the audience on to someone who just
represents something they're interested
in
sometimes charisma is more
physiologically in
emotionally authentic in a fantasy idea
of what a great archaic shaman was we
say that's what they partly were was
someone who was on open who was
available to the other someone who had
dealt with their own shadow material
someone who had recovered all of the
latent pseudo electrical charge that's
available to their own body and they
have it with them rather than having it
projected repressed suppressed a lot of
us think someone is charismatic they
acting in a way that represents an idea
that we like and we project our energy
onto them as we aren't in command of our
own stimulation patterns or that we can
on our own reactions and let that
excitation move through us the more
we're capable of being a distributed
community of fairly charismatic people
though the non charismatic people who
are obsessively projecting their own
latent charisma onto a performer of some
kind so I was really caught by this idea
of performance the way I envisioned it
is that there's a space that's generated
by the crowd right like a potential
resonance and that maybe there's the
performance is like a shamanistic
embodiment of that resonance and that
you could play with it right you could
steer it into the correct direction by
staying true to yourself and to the
world I guess so so you can focus that
energy in a general generative way
different ways to do it
octave Li basically if we we were piss
pataw really consciously involved in a
situation where we knew that we were
projecting our energy on to a guru of
some kind and he was feeding that energy
back to us
as well as critiquing our tendency to
project ourselves on to him could be a
really useful circumstance
often that's not the circumstance and
have to have our own critique and
responsibility of our tenants to project
our energy on to the other the surplus
energy of the other which was added to
our perception of them actually
occurring within us you need to be able
to locate that within us as a
stimulation pattern we can take
possession of it there are our own
developments one of the major problems
in terms of the previous question about
regression versus development intial
systems and individuals is have enough
energy in yourself and you have the
energy to undergo development in many
new things and bloom them into your
definition if you don't have energy you
become very starvation oriented guerra
city oriented you want to fall back to a
kind of purity and simplicity because
you don't have the energy to in full
diversity into your new definition think
that we need to be aware when we deal
with people who appear charismatic need
to be able to critique them and ask
ourselves whether or not that person is
actually what we mean charismatic to be
or whether the charisma we're looking at
is our own charisma being offloaded from
ourselves onto our imaginary idea of
them could work right I think a lot of
historical rituals involved someone
taking the spot of the group projection
being that back to you it's also a very
risky situation because they might not
handle it right
bite in in you into the pattern of
projection rather than into the of
receiving and consuming and feeding on
your own stimulation so I'm really
interested in that distinction between
feeding the shadow basically
and be channeling it into constructive
way can you expand on that it's the most
basic skill to do with somatic sensing
if you're looking at the person or idea
or system we find to be radiant and
charismatic should be paying attention
inside our own bodies to the emulation
patterns that go along with that
perception locate the feelings of
excitation along with the perception or
in a pretty good spot to be able to
start working with that excitation in
ourselves we don't feel ourselves and
all we do is conference radiant or
charismatic or fascinating person or
idea we're very close to a form of
hypnosis
she is 50/50 whether it's gonna turn out
to be good for us or destructive for it
yeah that's that's interesting
information need to chew on that Thanks
well surely the ratio isn't always 50/50
I just mean that it's a gamble like any
any time you were to go I do
hypnotherapy and any time you put
yourself in you allow yourself to go
into a trance that someone else is
guiding you're taking a risk I have to
trust them of some reason to believe
that the trance they enable you to go
into is going to be useful for you
rather than diluting misleading for you
do use their criteria to make the
evaluation right right so also doing
hypnotherapy I'm assuming you offer that
as a service then it so you do you have
the sense then that it's worthwhile to
just spend an extended period of time
getting to know them and have them get
to trust you before you perform the
service or is it is it something that
can be done in a relatively short period
of time
depends a lot upon the individual hey I
would prefer they spent Mort for some
people they have need is much more
urgent and they're much more willing to
take the risk yeah I I tend to do it in
a certain way that satisfies my own
conscience which is I try to do as
little directing as a bowl but I can
feel secure about how I work with them
san sees that there's an intelligence in
the unconscious in the trance state
itself
I can evoke in them and it will guide
them rather than telling me their
problem and me hypothetically helping
them out with it right I mean
hypothetically in the sense that they
have no absolute reason to believe I'm
going to be helpful um but what I try to
do is them in touch with a part of
themselves that's smarter than they are
is yes right that's exactly how I
describe it here very often
that there's there's obviously something
going on than there the straights
extraordinary capacity you see it
isolated from time to time and things
like idiot savants or some found
cognitive function and you know it's
certainly demonstrated in like the
psychedelic experience right where
there's some kind of self-organizing re
understanding of the world that's
presented in some strange way yeah like
really did let people become unafraid of
speaking what they truly desire and then
presenting to that desire and in a
receptive way they seem to work it out
themselves world that we're in right now
it is on such chaos and complexity in
every direction there it's the absolute
mass weirdness of going on the level of
the economy and politics and
civilization whether it's the increasing
discoveries of chaos science and
complexity science and computationally
reduce
ability and scales of the universe that
we can barely comprehend the complexity
of the situation we face the
overwhelming and we need our
intelligence systems that are better
than us so to speak and that means
collective intelligence computational
intelligence and subconscious
intelligence those all are only
effective when we can encourage them to
actually operate a level that's more
sophisticated than we are right now the
full stack yeah I think it's I think
it's vital that we I mean this is kind
of like an educational protocol right
like it to be plugged into each of this
in terms of understanding how they
interrelate and becoming proficient at
the tools that are used at each of those
layers I think that is what produces a
functionally well-rounded individual the
information eco sphere that you've got
so despite the kinds of dogmatic and
sectarian violence that have been
associated with religion over the years
there's something deeply religious about
all these forms of higher intelligence
collective relative to the individual
and the subconscious relative to the
conscious mutational relative to our
linear capacity to understand things
it's a huge gap of mystery it's almost
like each one of these areas an area in
which we have to cross a mystery in
order to deal with the super
intelligence the fundamental pattern
brought forward in religions over human
history yeah my my computer frequently
evokes the feeling of awe but just as
often I curse it
thanks a lot for doing this by the way
this is great these are fantastic
questions and everybody seems really
sincere and engaged so yeah yeah I've
been consistently impressed by the
people that show up in these places a
lot of them yeah well this has been
another fascinating hour and yeah thank
you thank you again for coming you know
I feel there's just like a well a deep
well of information to dive into every
time every time we speak and you know
well I guess I should ask are there any
resources you could recommend you know
for learning a little bit more about
feminism today and I don't know if
there's some good YouTube series I wanna
add I would say read the classics read
more che le Adi read Terence Mckenna
people like that more fundamental than
accessing those resources say you know
go into nature be immersed in the
ecosystem do it with drugs do it with
drumming with trances do it with
whatever you can but go out there hybrid
state of consciousness and try to make
contact with elements the biosphere
learn so much more than you would learn
from a book or a youtube series don't
conclude so we have some more practices
to come up with our nature exploration
practices as well like it again thank
you so much for this this has been great
we'd love to have you back anytime I
thank everybody for for the fantastic
questions and I'm always so grateful
that everybody that you all come to
these events will be uploading it to to
youtube so please everyone subscribe to
our
YouTube channel and remember John's
gonna be back here on Monday for for
another for his bi-weekly QA and make
sure to subscribe to our Google Calendar
because we've had we have tons of events
pretty well every day so so please
yeah please make sure you you keep up
with everything that we're doing so
thanks again Lehman this has been just a
wonderful hour my pleasure I happy to
come back sometime thank you thank you
so much that was brilliant